<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="https://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="https://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="https://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[Research - Cybernetic Implantable Devices Lab]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Cybernetic Implantable Devices Lab focuses on the design and manufacturing of implantable medical devices.]]></description><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/</link><image><url>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/favicon.png</url><title>Research - Cybernetic Implantable Devices Lab</title><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/</link></image><generator>Ghost 5.33</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 13:44:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/tag/research/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Development of closed-loop feedback algorithms and stimulation to modulate gastric functions]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Gastrointestinal (GI) symptoms are widespread, with large economic and social consequences. In 2010 alone, an estimated 60-70 million Americans suffered from a chronic digestive disease such as gastroparesis. The evidence base for the use of electric stimulation to treat diseases like gastroparesis is still very limited. Modulating gastric function is</p>]]></description><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/research/treating-gastrointestinal-disea/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e41598562</guid><category><![CDATA[Research Topics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 17:51:56 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/09/Picture1.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/09/Picture1.png" alt="Development of closed-loop feedback algorithms and stimulation to modulate gastric functions"><p>Gastrointestinal (GI) symptoms are widespread, with large economic and social consequences. In 2010 alone, an estimated 60-70 million Americans suffered from a chronic digestive disease such as gastroparesis. The evidence base for the use of electric stimulation to treat diseases like gastroparesis is still very limited. Modulating gastric function is an important target function for electroceutical devices looking to provide therapy. Recording gastric motility in freely behaving animal models will form the needed foundation for neuromodulation protocols that can correct shortcomings in past, first-generation bioelectronic attempts to ameliorate and monitor gastric disorders. We are developing a fully implantable system capable of recording serosal gastric myoelectrical activity using electrogastrography (EGG) as well as stomach contractile activity using strain gauge transducers, in collaboration with researchers at &#xA0;Purdue University and the University of Melbourne. Validation in freely behaving rodent models represents the first instance of continuous measurement of gastrointestinal motility in freely moving animal models. Subsequent validation in pigs represents large animal preclinical proof-of-principle and opens the door to future work investigating the development of closed-loop feedback algorithms and stimulation to modulate gastric function.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Extra-Occular Stimulation to Treat Glaucoma]]></title><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/research/glaucoma/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e41598555</guid><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research Topics]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 06:23:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/photo-1615552441070-cbe0d49f5ae9.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded/></item><item><title><![CDATA[Photoactivated Ion Channel Blockers for Heart Attack Treatment]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Acute myocardial infarctions (heart attacks, AMI) occur almost 800,000 times a year in the US. They result from blockages in the coronary arteries (the blood vessels that feed the heart oxygen) and can be treated with catheters that enter the arteries through the arm or leg and snake their</p>]]></description><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/research/photoactivated-ion-channel-blockers/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e41598559</guid><category><![CDATA[Research Topics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 19:04:13 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/DALL-E-2022-08-30-15.03.31---Fiber-optics-in-the-heart.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/DALL-E-2022-08-30-15.03.31---Fiber-optics-in-the-heart.png" alt="Photoactivated Ion Channel Blockers for Heart Attack Treatment"><p>Acute myocardial infarctions (heart attacks, AMI) occur almost 800,000 times a year in the US. They result from blockages in the coronary arteries (the blood vessels that feed the heart oxygen) and can be treated with catheters that enter the arteries through the arm or leg and snake their way up, tipped with an inflatable balloon and sometimes a metal stent. The balloon is inflated to compress the material blocking the artery against the walls, introducing a lumen that can be held open with the stent. However, abrupt reintroduction of blood (also known as reperfusion) causes reversal of the sodium-calcium exchanger (NCX), a passive ion channel that operates in reverse and causes heart muscle death through calcium imbalances. With collaborators at the Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#xED;ficas in Madrid, Spain and the Universitari Vall d&apos;Hebron - Institut de Recerca in Barcelona, Spain, we are creating NCX inhibitors that can be activated and deactivated when illuminated by different wavelengths of light. Using flexible optic fibers, optical focusing systems, and efficient LED-based electronics, we can modulate the NCX-inhibitor alongside the balloon catheter, improving reperfusion outcomes by minimizing heart muscle death.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Recording Neuron Activity using Implantable Fluorescence Sensors]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Neurostimulation is an effective way to modulate the nervous system to treat diseases and disorders like drug-resistant epilepsy, depression, and Parkinson&#x2019;s. Stimulation acts by creating a local electric field with an electrode outside of an axon, inducing changes in voltage-gated ion channels that create an action potential (AP)</p>]]></description><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/research/a-render-of-neurons-firing-light/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e4159855a</guid><category><![CDATA[Research Topics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 18:56:41 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/DALL-E-2022-08-30-14.54.15---A-render-of-neurons-firing-light.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/DALL-E-2022-08-30-14.54.15---A-render-of-neurons-firing-light.png" alt="Recording Neuron Activity using Implantable Fluorescence Sensors"><p>Neurostimulation is an effective way to modulate the nervous system to treat diseases and disorders like drug-resistant epilepsy, depression, and Parkinson&#x2019;s. Stimulation acts by creating a local electric field with an electrode outside of an axon, inducing changes in voltage-gated ion channels that create an action potential (AP). For stimulation to be effective, the strength of the created electric field creates a Goldilocks problem &#x2013; too small of an amplitude fails to activate the axon(s) in question and too large of an amplitude activates undesired axons that can signal the wrong direction or stimulate unintended organs and muscles. Electrical recordings or muscle twitches are used to find stimulation thresholds (by ramping up stimulation amplitude until AP is seen) but recording electrodes must be placed far from stimulation electrodes to avoid stimulation artifact, increasing the implant footprint (larger devices block more blood flow, creating necrotic tissue and eliciting more inflammatory response). We are working on a system that records action potentials chemically by measuring neurotransmitter and ion concentrations at synapses of interest. Using fluorophore-embedded waveguides and implantable miniaturized optics and electronics, we are working to improve the Bionode to both stimulate and record neurons simultaneously.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Next Generation Neuromodulation]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Electrical stimulation of nerves, or neuromodulation, is the state-of-the-art treatment for several diseases which cannot be treated through traditional pharmacological interventions such as Parkinson&#x2019;s disease or refractory epilepsy. With growing clinical interest in applying neuromodulation to new problems, the development of high-quality neuromodulation techniques is paramount. Here at</p>]]></description><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/research/next-generation-neuromodulation/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e41598563</guid><category><![CDATA[Research Topics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2022 17:54:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/09/image--1-.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/09/image--1-.png" alt="Next Generation Neuromodulation"><p>Electrical stimulation of nerves, or neuromodulation, is the state-of-the-art treatment for several diseases which cannot be treated through traditional pharmacological interventions such as Parkinson&#x2019;s disease or refractory epilepsy. With growing clinical interest in applying neuromodulation to new problems, the development of high-quality neuromodulation techniques is paramount. Here at the CID, we leverage our unique position and expertise both to develop the hardware tools to perform neuromodulation, and then test these tools in real animal studies to validate their efficacy. Specifically, we have experience in traditional biphasic stimulation, pulson stimulation for fiber selectivity, and temporal interference stimulation (also known as interferential current stimulation) for spatial selectivity.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Improved Seizure Prediction with Reinforcement Learning Controlled Filtering Hardware]]></title><description><![CDATA[What if analog filtering circuits were co-designed with ML feedback to create an entirely new learning signal acquisition hardware?]]></description><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/research/rl-seizure-prediction/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e41598554</guid><category><![CDATA[Research Topics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 20:47:52 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/photo-1655720845034-b8f615109b5b-4.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/photo-1655720845034-b8f615109b5b-4.jpg" alt="Improved Seizure Prediction with Reinforcement Learning Controlled Filtering Hardware"><p>Analog filtering circuits are typically static; amplifying and filtering data as specified by the designer. This is sufficient when the features of the desired output are known, but when they are not, the designer must make assumptions. Therefore, the resulting data might not contain all the necessary information needed to characterize the signal of interest. Machine learning (ML) algorithms have repeatedly demonstrated their ability to learn from large, complex datasets, identify hidden features, and make advantageous decisions in ways that meet or exceed human ability; but they are only as good as the data from which they learn, potentially limiting performance. <strong>What if analog filtering circuits were co-designed with ML feedback to create an entirely new learning signal acquisition hardware?</strong> </p><p>Reinforcement &#xA0;learning &#xA0;(RL), &#xA0;one &#xA0;of &#xA0;the &#xA0;three paradigms of ML, is based on rewarding a computational agent for desired behaviors as it explores an interactive environment, learning through trial-and-error by using feedback &#xA0;from &#xA0;its &#xA0;own &#xA0;actions &#xA0;and &#xA0;experiences &#xA0;to optimize a cumulative reward. <strong>We propose the creation of an RL algorithm that derives states and rewards from the &#xA0;validation &#xA0;outputs &#xA0;of &#xA0;a &#xA0;classification-based supervised &#xA0;learning &#xA0;(SL) &#xA0;algorithm, &#xA0;another &#xA0;ML paradigm. </strong> The &#xA0;RL &#xA0;algorithm &#xA0;acts &#xA0;on &#xA0;tunable analog filtering hardware that filters the data from which the SL algorithm learns. This dual optimization will enable the isolation of key characteristics for the signal &#xA0;of &#xA0;interest &#xA0;with &#xA0;hardware &#xA0;filtering &#xA0;whilst simultaneously &#xA0;improving &#xA0;the &#xA0;performance of &#xA0;the &#xA0;SL algorithm.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Deep Learning in Epilepsy]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Epilepsy is a disease involving the spontaneous occurrence of seizure events, which can be dangerous when they occur and are also debilitating to patients&apos; daily lives due to their unpredictability. Developing methods to monitor and study this disease is difficult and time consuming as patients often must be studied</p>]]></description><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/research/deep-learning-in-epilepsy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e41598553</guid><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research Topics]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 20:27:23 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/photo-1655635949348-953b0e3c140a-1.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/photo-1655635949348-953b0e3c140a-1.jpg" alt="Deep Learning in Epilepsy"><p>Epilepsy is a disease involving the spontaneous occurrence of seizure events, which can be dangerous when they occur and are also debilitating to patients&apos; daily lives due to their unpredictability. Developing methods to monitor and study this disease is difficult and time consuming as patients often must be studied individually due the highly variable physiology. The emerging field of Machine Learning (ML) and Deep Learning (DL) based algorithms presents a unique opportunity in this space to develop personalized algorithms tuned to each specific patient after initial recording of some representative data. Here at CID we are working to integrate existing ML and DL techniques with our devices and custom datasets to develop algorithms which can analyze, detect, and predict seizure events in real time with never-before-seen accuracy. We are also working to develop new DL techniques that are optimized for time-series biological data and the types of signals that are often collected in biomedical contexts. All of the code and resources we develop to pursue this goal will be made freely available upon publication to other researchers and companies to aid in the development and deployment of highly successful algorithms for epilepsy patients and others in need of sophisticated personalized signal analysis.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[ML Framework: Toast API]]></title><description><![CDATA[The toast library contains general-use functions used in algorithm development for CID.]]></description><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/toast/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e41598550</guid><category><![CDATA[CID Resources]]></category><category><![CDATA[Software]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/photo-1619095762086-66b82f914dcf.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/photo-1619095762086-66b82f914dcf.jpg" alt="ML Framework: Toast API"><p>Toast is a Python library with a collection of general-use functions that are commonly used in the development of algorithms for the Cybernetic Implantable Devices Lab (CID). These functions are useful in performing a variety of tasks relevant to machine learning including data segmentation, labeling and processing. Also included are frameworks for model fitting, feature generation, model selection, model evaluation, and other numerical computations. </p><p>The library is designed to be highly modular and easy to use, making it a useful tool for both researchers and engineers working in the field of machine learning. Overall, the toast library aims to provide a set of powerful and flexible tools for developing cutting-edge machine learning models.</p><hr><div class="kg-card kg-button-card kg-align-center"><a href="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/toast-docs/" class="kg-btn kg-btn-accent">&#x1F517; API Reference</a></div><hr>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Chronic Epilepsy Monitoring for Dataset Creation]]></title><link>https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/research/chronic-epilepsy-monitoring-for-dataset-creation/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63e3ca757644608e41598556</guid><category><![CDATA[Research]]></category><category><![CDATA[Research Topics]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[CID]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://cid.wse.jhu.edu/content/images/2022/08/photo-1655635643486-a17bc48771ff.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded/></item></channel></rss>